## SARANSH CHOPRA

🏶 saransh-cpp.github.io | 🛥 saransh0701@gmail.com | 🛅 saransh-cpp | 🗘 Saransh-cpp | 💆 WhiteViolin

#### About

Saransh is an engineering junior who, by day, works on his academic and professional commitments, and by night, develops and maintains open-source research software, which he believes are the key to collaborative and reproducible research.

He is passionate about Research Software Engineering, Machine Learning, Scientific Machine Learning, and Open-Source Research Software.

#### Education

University of Delhi
Major: Information Technology and Mathematical Innovations

New Delhi, India
2020 - 2024

Minor: Computational Biology CGPA 9.46

Research and Work Experience

# Institute for Research and Innovation in Software for High Energy Physics, Princeton University

June 2022 - September 2022

IRIS-HEP research fellow [Funded by IRIS-HEP]

Dr. Henry Schreiner (Princeton University / CERN) and Dr. Jim Pivarski (Princeton University / CERN)

• Prepared Vector for v0.9.0 and v1.0.0 (first major release) by developing new public API, fixing bugs, and building new

- infrastructure.
- The major release is currently being used by researcher at CERN, ATLAS, CMS, etc. to construct 4D jagged (awkward) vectors and perform Just-In-Time compiled vector operations in Python.
- Worked closely with CERN and Princeton researchers, and IRIS-HEP maintainers.

### FluxML, The Julia Programming Language

Remote

Remote

Open-source developer and technical writer [Funded by The Julia Programming Language] May 2022 – September 2022 Mr. Dhairya Gandhi

- Fixed bugs and developed the infrastructure of prominent Julia ML libraries such as Flux.jl, NNlib.jl (Neural Network primitives), Metalhead.jl (Computer vision models), and Functors.jl.
- Wrote original Machine Learning/Deep Learning tutorials, documentation and API references for FluxML's ecosystem.
- Worked closely with doctoral researchers and FluxML maintainers from around the world.

#### PyBaMM, NumFOCUS

Remote

Google Summer of Code student developer [Funded by Google]

May 2021 - August 2021

Dr. Valentin Sulzer (Carnegie Melon University), Dr. Robert Timms (University of Oxford), Dr. Ferran Brosa Planella (University of Warwick)

- Built an automated Twitter Bot capable of constructing Mathematical Simulations of Batteries, including but not limited to different battery models, parameter sets, chemistries, degradation modes, and experiments.
- Developed a replying functionality to run Mathematical Simulations on command, created a CI/CD pipeline, and followed a micro-services-based architecture.
- Worked closely with post-doctoral research fellows and PyBaMM maintainers from around the world.

#### **Publications**

[Tra+21] T. G. Tranter, R. Timms, V. Sulzer, F. B. Planella, G. M. Wiggins, S. V. Karra, P. Agarwal, S. Chopra, S. Allu, P. R. Shearing, and D. J. L. Brett. *liionpack: A Python package for simulating packs of batteries with PyBaMM*. Journal of Open Source Software, 7(70), 4051. Oct. 2021. DOI: https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.04051.

## Open Source Research Software

#### **PyBaMM**

Maintainer and Core Developer - 215,000+ installs - 420+ stars

PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling) solves physics-based electrochemical DAE models by using state-of-the-art automatic differentiation and numerical solvers.

 ${f Vector}$ 

Collaborater and Core Developer - 72,000+ installs - 40+ stars

Vector is a Python 3.6+ library for 2D, 3D, and Lorentz vectors, especially arrays of vectors, to solve common physics problems in a NumPy-like way.

#### Flux.jl

Core contributor - 80,000+ installs - 3,700+ stars

Flux is an elegant approach to machine learning. It's a 100% pure-Julia stack, and provides lightweight abstractions on top of Julia's native GPU and AD support. Flux makes the easy things easy while remaining fully hackable.

**BattBot** 

Maintainer and Core Developer - 130+ followers - 10+ stars

An automated Twitter Bot that Tweets random Battery Mathematical Modeling Simulations and replies to the requested Battery Simulations.

liionpack

Maintainer and Core Developer - 2,000+ installs - 30+ stars

liionpack takes a 1D PyBaMM model and makes it into a pack. You can either specify the configuration e.g. 16 cells in parallel and 2 in series (16p2s) or load a netlist.

## Other notable contributions

- **DeepXDE**: DeepXDE is a library for scientific machine learning 330,000+ installs 1,200+ stars Implemented utility functions and improved the existing examples on solving partial differential equations using Physics-Informed neural networks.
- Colour: Colour Science for Python 6,000,000+ installs 1,500+ stars Implemented the conversion between RGB and HCL colourspaces.

#### Posters and Presentations

- [SSP22a] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Compiling Awkward Lorentz vectors with Numba. 21st International Workshop on Advanced Computing and Analysis Techniques in Physics Research. Poster (upcoming). Oct. 2022. URL: https://indi.to/45Kzq.
- [SSP22b] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Constructing HEP vectors and analyzing HEP data using Vector. PyHEP (Python in High Energy Physics) workshop. Presentation (upcoming). Oct. 2022. URL: https://indico.cern.ch/event/1150631/abstracts/147762/.
- [S C22a] S. Chopra. Python packaging: from stone age to the future. PyDelhi workshop. Presentation (upcoming). Sept. 2022.
- [S C22b] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. PyCon Asia-Pacific (APAC). Presentation (upcoming). Sept. 2022. URL: https://tw.pycon.org/2022/en-us/conference/talk/243.
- [S C22c] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. EuroPython. Presentation. July 2022. URL: https://ep2022.europython.eu/session/code-coverage-through-unit-tests-running-in-sub-processes-threads-locally-and-automated-on-github.
- [S C22d] S. Chopra. Vector Constructors, documentation, and benchmarks. IRIS-HEP Lightning Talks. Presentation. June 2022. URL: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fLt7BHuASpw.
- [S C21] S. Chopra. BattBot: Mathematical Modeling of Batteries using an automated Twitter bot. PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modeling) training workshop. Presentation. Oct. 2021. URL: https://www.pybamm.org/training.

## Grants, Prizes and Achievements

$July\ 2022$
June 2022
June~2022
$April\ 2022$
$November\ 2021$
May 2021

• Discovered an asteroid having a fixed orbit around Sun by analysing the data Pan-STARRS observatory

August 2016

## **Projects**

OCRed [OCR, Computer Vision, Python library, Research software, GH Actions, GH Pages]

August 2022

- OCRed provides clever, simple, and intuitive wrapper functionalities for OCRing specific textual materials.
- The Python library has 800+ installs on PyPI, 10+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

ForMente [NLP, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Python, Firebase, Firestore, Heroku, GitHub Actions]

June 2022

- Using Natural Language Processing, ForMente lets you diagnose your feelings in the form of a secure personal diary.
- The NLP model is deployed on Heroku using FastAPI, and the app uses Firebase and Firestore as its backend.

ChaoticEncryption.jl [Image processing, Encryption algorithms, ODEs, PRNGs, Julia package]

February 2022

- Vectorised image encryption and PRNG algorithms that runs ~40X faster than ordinary nested-for implementations.
- The Julia package has 10+ installs on JuliHub and 25+ stars on GitHub.

#### PDEsWithPINNs [PDEs, PINNs, Python, DeepXDE]

January 2022

- Worked under Prof. Shobha Bagai to solve 1, 2, 3, and 4D Partial Differential Equations using Physics-Informed Neural Networks.
- Worked with Neural tangent Kernels, Multi-scale Fourier feature networks, and Spatio-temporal Multi-scale Fourier feature networks to predict high-frequency details.

## Mentorship

## Google Summer of Code

May - September 2022

• Mentored students under PyBaMM, NumFOCUS, on projects involving, but not limited to, documentation, DevOps, parameterisation, and visualization.

CodePeak December 2021

• Mentored 10+ students in the field of open-source application development.

#### Relevant Skills

Languages: Julia | Python | C/C++ | JavaScript | Dart

Frameworks/Libraries: Tensorflow | FluxML-Ecosystem | PyTorch | PyData-Ecosystem | SciML-Ecosystem | DeepXDE

Flutter | FastAPI | NodeJS

Research Interests: Machine Learning | Scientific ML | Research Software Development | OSS Research Software

## Languages

Hindi (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (basic), Punjabi (conversational)